<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML 5.0//EN"
"http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/dtd/docbook.dtd"[
]>
<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more contributor
	license agreements. See the NOTICE file distributed with this work for additional
	information regarding copyright ownership. The ASF licenses this file to
	you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use
	this file except in compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy of
	the License at http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0 Unless required
	by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed under the
	License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS
	OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the License for the specific
	language governing permissions and limitations under the License. -->

<chapter xml:id="tools.assets" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">

	<title>Embedded Asset Detection</title>

	<section xml:id="tools.assets.introduction">
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>
			Text dumps carry binaries: web pages inline images as <code>data:</code> URIs,
			documents paste base64 payloads, and hostile bodies smuggle encoded content.
			The package <code>opennlp.tools.assets</code> finds such assets as exact spans
			over the original text, identifies their format, and can replace them with text
			while keeping every offset mapped to the source.
		</para>
		<para>
			Identification needs no decoding pass: when a payload starts at a file's first
			byte, the file magic has a fixed base64 image, so detection is literal matching
			inside base64 runs. A PNG payload always starts <code>iVBORw0KGgo</code>, a
			JPEG <code>/9j/</code>, a GIF <code>R0lGOD</code>, a RIFF container
			<code>UklGR</code>, a PDF <code>JVBERi0</code>, and a zip archive
			<code>UEsDB</code>. The built-in table ranges across image, document, archive,
			audio, video, font, database, certificate, and executable formats, PNG to
			Parquet to PEM-armored keys; the magic values are derived from the leading
			bytes each format's specification publishes and from the mime-type catalog
			of Apache Tika. Only a magic anchored at the first byte can be scanned for
			this way, so a container whose signature sits at a later offset, such as the
			ISO base media format of MP4, is out of scope for bare runs. Signatures that
			classify loose prose rather than a file, such as mail header lines or
			source-code conventions, are deliberately absent. A bare run is only
			reported when it is long enough to be a real payload, carries such a prefix,
			and its decoded leading bytes verify the magic; a <code>data:</code> URI
			declares its media type and is reported at any payload length. Decoding the
			leading bytes also yields image dimensions where the format's header carries
			them.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="tools.assets.detection">
		<title>Detecting and decoding</title>
		<para>
			The example below embeds a minimal 5x7 PNG as a data URI:
			<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
String text = "An image data:image/png;base64,"
    + "iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAAAUAAAAHCAYAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA"
    + " follows.";

AssetDetector detector = new CursorAssetDetector();
EmbeddedAsset asset = detector.detect(text).get(0);
// asset.format()        = "png"
// asset.mediaType()     = "image/png"
// asset.width()         = 5
// asset.height()        = 7
// asset.decodedLength() = 45
byte[] bytes = asset.decode(text);  // the original 45 bytes]]>
			</programlisting>
			The asset's span covers the whole URI; its payload span covers just the
			base64 characters, and <code>decode</code> reads them straight from the
			original text.
			<code>AssetsManualExampleTest</code> asserts the behavior shown here.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="tools.assets.fold">
		<title>Folding assets into text</title>
		<para>
			<code>AssetAnnotator</code> provides the <code>opennlp:assets</code> layer, and
			<code>AssetFolder</code> replaces every asset with text. The result is an
			<code>AlignedText</code>: spans over the folded text map back to exact original
			offsets, so downstream findings over the cleaned text still locate in the raw
			input. The default replacement renders a caption from the asset's own
			metadata:
			<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
Document document = new AssetAnnotator().annotate(Document.of(text));
AlignedText folded = AssetFolder.fold(document, AssetFolder.caption());
// folded.normalizedString() = "An image [png 5x7, 45 bytes] follows."]]>
			</programlisting>
			Mapping the caption back recovers the asset's exact span in the original:
			<code>folded.toOriginalSpan(9, 28)</code>, the caption's offsets in the folded
			text, returns the span of the whole data URI.
		</para>
		<para>
			What replaces an asset is the caller's choice through the replacement
			function. A <code>BinaryContentDescriber</code>, the seam for external binary
			understanding such as document text extraction or image description, composes
			in directly:
			<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
BinaryContentDescriber describer = ...;  // supplied by the caller

AlignedText described = AssetFolder.fold(document, annotation ->
    describer.describe(annotation.value().decode(text),
        annotation.value().mediaType()));]]>
			</programlisting>
			The interface takes bytes and a media type and returns text. Implementations
			are constructor-injected, so integrating one adds no dependency to this
			toolkit; any dependency injection container can register an implementation as
			a bean unchanged.
		</para>
	</section>
</chapter>
