<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML 5.0//EN"
"http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/dtd/docbook.dtd"[
]>
<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more contributor
	license agreements. See the NOTICE file distributed with this work for additional
	information regarding copyright ownership. The ASF licenses this file to
	you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use
	this file except in compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy of
	the License at http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0 Unless required
	by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed under the
	License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS
	OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the License for the specific
	language governing permissions and limitations under the License. -->

<chapter xml:id="tools.document" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">

	<title>The Document Model</title>

	<section xml:id="tools.document.introduction">
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>
			The package <code>opennlp.tools.document</code> provides a container that carries a
			piece of text together with every annotation produced from it. Where the individual
			tools in this manual each read one kind of input and return one kind of output, the
			document model gives those outputs a common home: a single immutable object that holds
			the original text and any number of typed annotation layers over it. Sentence
			boundaries, tokens, part-of-speech tags, names, and any layer an application defines all
			live side by side, each addressable by a typed key.
		</para>
		<para>
			Two properties make the container useful as the backbone of a processing pipeline.
			First, every annotation is anchored to the original text by character offsets, and those
			offsets never change: a token span read back after ten further stages still indexes the
			exact substring it covered when it was produced. Second, the container is immutable.
			Adding a layer returns a new document rather than mutating the old one, so a document can
			be shared across threads without copying and a pipeline is a plain sequence of
			pure functions.
		</para>
		<para>
			The chapters that follow describe the components that produce these layers: sentence
			detection, tokenization, part-of-speech tagging, name finding, and the rest. This
			chapter describes the container they share and the small interface an annotator
			implements to take part in a pipeline.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="tools.document.model">
		<title>Documents and annotations</title>
		<para>
			A <code>Document</code> is created from a piece of text and starts with no layers:
			<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[Document document = Document.of("Rockwell International Corp. said it signed an agreement.");]]></programlisting>
			The original text is always available and is never rewritten to a derived form:
			<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[CharSequence text = document.text();]]></programlisting>
		</para>
		<para>
			An annotation is a span of the text paired with a value. The span uses the same
			<code>opennlp.tools.util.Span</code> type used elsewhere in the library, and its start
			and end are offsets into <code>document.text()</code>. The value type is whatever the
			layer carries: a string for a token or a tag, a richer record for a structured layer.
			<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[public record Annotation<T>(Span span, T value) { }]]></programlisting>
			Because the span always refers to the original text, an annotation produced by a later
			stage can be lined up with one from an earlier stage without any offset bookkeeping. A
			part-of-speech tag and the token it describes share the same span.
		</para>
		<para>
			A document exposes the layers it holds, the annotations on any one layer, and a method
			that returns a new document with an added layer.
			<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[List<Annotation<String>> tokens = List.of(
    new Annotation<>(new Span(0, 8), "Rockwell"));

Document tokenized = document.with(Layers.TOKENS, tokens);

Set<LayerKey<?>> present = tokenized.layers();       // contains Layers.TOKENS
List<Annotation<String>> readBack = tokenized.get(Layers.TOKENS);]]></programlisting>
			The original <code>document</code> is unchanged by <code>with</code>: it still has no
			token layer, while <code>tokenized</code> carries it. A document holds at most one layer
			per key, so <code>with</code> rejects an attempt to add a layer the document already has;
			an annotator produces a layer once. Reading a layer that is not present returns an empty
			list rather than <code>null</code>.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="tools.document.layers">
		<title>Layers and typed keys</title>
		<para>
			A layer is identified by a <code>LayerKey</code>, which pairs a string identifier with
			the value type carried on that layer. The type parameter is what makes
			<code>document.get(Layers.TOKENS)</code> return a
			<code>List&lt;Annotation&lt;String&gt;&gt;</code> without a cast: the key carries the
			type, and the compiler checks that reads and writes agree.
			<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[LayerKey<String> tokens = LayerKey.of("tokens", String.class);]]></programlisting>
			Two keys are equal when both their identifier and their type are equal, so a key can be
			reconstructed anywhere from the same identifier and class and will address the same
			layer.
		</para>
		<para>
			The <code>Layers</code> class holds the keys the built-in annotators use, so
			applications and annotators refer to the same layers by the same constants:
			<informaltable frame="all">
				<tgroup cols="2">
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>Key</entry>
							<entry>Value</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry><code>Layers.SENTENCES</code></entry>
							<entry>one annotation per sentence</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><code>Layers.TOKENS</code></entry>
							<entry>one annotation per token, value is the token text</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><code>Layers.POS_TAGS</code></entry>
							<entry>one annotation per token, value is the tag</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><code>Layers.ENTITIES</code></entry>
							<entry>one annotation per detected name, value is the type</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</informaltable>
			An application defines its own layer by declaring a key of its own type. Nothing about
			the container is specific to the built-in layers; a custom layer is a first-class
			citizen addressed exactly like the built-in ones.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="tools.document.annotators">
		<title>Annotators</title>
		<para>
			A <code>DocumentAnnotator</code> reads the layers it needs from a document and returns a
			document with the layer it produces added. The interface is small:
			<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[public interface DocumentAnnotator {

  Document annotate(Document document);

  default Set<LayerKey<?>> requires() {
    return Set.of();
  }

  Set<LayerKey<?>> provides();
}]]></programlisting>
			The <code>requires</code> and <code>provides</code> sets declare the annotator's
			place in a pipeline: what layers must already be present for it to run, and what layers
			it adds. An annotator that needs nothing keeps the default empty <code>requires</code>.
		</para>
		<para>
			The library ships annotators that adapt the existing tools to this interface. Each wraps
			a trained model or component and declares its layers:
			<informaltable frame="all">
				<tgroup cols="3">
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>Annotator</entry>
							<entry>Requires</entry>
							<entry>Provides</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry><code>SentenceDetectorAnnotator</code></entry>
							<entry>nothing</entry>
							<entry><code>SENTENCES</code></entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><code>TokenizerAnnotator</code></entry>
							<entry>nothing; uses <code>SENTENCES</code> when present</entry>
							<entry><code>TOKENS</code></entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><code>POSTaggerAnnotator</code></entry>
							<entry><code>TOKENS</code></entry>
							<entry><code>POS_TAGS</code></entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><code>NameFinderAnnotator</code></entry>
							<entry><code>TOKENS</code></entry>
							<entry><code>ENTITIES</code></entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</informaltable>
			The tokenizer adapter shows the offset discipline the container relies on. When the
			sentence layer is present it tokenizes each sentence separately, then shifts each token
			span back into original-text coordinates, so a token span read from the finished
			document indexes the original text directly and not the sentence it was found in.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="tools.document.analyzer">
		<title>Running a pipeline</title>
		<para>
			A <code>DocumentAnalyzer</code> holds an ordered list of annotators and runs them over a
			piece of text. It is assembled with a builder:
			<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[DocumentAnalyzer analyzer = DocumentAnalyzer.builder()
    .add(new SentenceDetectorAnnotator(sentenceDetector))
    .add(new TokenizerAnnotator(tokenizer))
    .add(new POSTaggerAnnotator(posTagger))
    .build();

Document document = analyzer.analyze("Rockwell International Corp. said it signed an agreement.");]]></programlisting>
			The analyzer creates a document from the text and hands it to each annotator in turn,
			passing the document returned by one annotator to the next. Because each
			<code>annotate</code> call returns a new document, the analyzer simply threads the
			document through the sequence.
		</para>
		<para>
			The builder checks the pipeline when it is built. Each annotator's
			<code>requires</code> set must be satisfied by the layers that earlier annotators
			<code>provides</code>, or the build fails rather than leaving a pipeline that would break
			at run time. Adding <code>POSTaggerAnnotator</code> before anything provides
			<code>TOKENS</code>, for example, is rejected at build time.
		</para>
		<para>
			Once the document is analyzed, its layers are read back with the same keys the
			annotators used to write them:
			<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[List<Annotation<String>> tokens = document.get(Layers.TOKENS);
List<Annotation<String>> tags = document.get(Layers.POS_TAGS);

for (int i = 0; i < tokens.size(); i++) {
  Span span = tokens.get(i).span();
  System.out.println(tokens.get(i).value() + "/" + tags.get(i).value()
      + " at [" + span.getStart() + ".." + span.getEnd() + "]");
}]]></programlisting>
		</para>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="tools.document.custom">
		<title>Writing a custom annotator</title>
		<para>
			An application adds its own analysis by implementing <code>DocumentAnnotator</code>. The
			annotator below reads the token layer and produces a layer of acronyms, tokens of two or
			more characters that are written entirely in uppercase letters. It declares its own key,
			requires <code>TOKENS</code>, and provides the new layer.
			<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[public class AcronymAnnotator implements DocumentAnnotator {

  public static final LayerKey<String> ACRONYMS =
      LayerKey.of("acronyms", String.class);

  @Override
  public Set<LayerKey<?>> requires() {
    return Set.of(Layers.TOKENS);
  }

  @Override
  public Set<LayerKey<?>> provides() {
    return Set.of(ACRONYMS);
  }

  @Override
  public Document annotate(Document document) {
    List<Annotation<String>> acronyms = new ArrayList<>();
    for (Annotation<String> token : document.get(Layers.TOKENS)) {
      if (isAcronym(token.value())) {
        acronyms.add(new Annotation<>(token.span(), token.value()));
      }
    }
    return document.with(ACRONYMS, acronyms);
  }

  private static boolean isAcronym(String form) {
    if (form.length() < 2) {
      return false;
    }
    for (int i = 0; i < form.length(); i++) {
      if (!Character.isUpperCase(form.charAt(i))) {
        return false;
      }
    }
    return true;
  }
}]]></programlisting>
			Reusing the token span for each acronym keeps the new layer anchored to the same
			original-text offsets as the tokens it was derived from. The annotator drops into a
			pipeline like any other, and because it declares that it requires <code>TOKENS</code>,
			the builder guarantees a tokenizer runs before it.
		</para>
	</section>

</chapter>
