<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML 5.0//EN"
"http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/dtd/docbook.dtd"[
]>
<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more contributor
	license agreements. See the NOTICE file distributed with this work for additional
	information regarding copyright ownership. The ASF licenses this file to
	you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use
	this file except in compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy of
	the License at http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0 Unless required
	by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed under the
	License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS
	OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the License for the specific
	language governing permissions and limitations under the License. -->

<chapter xml:id="tools.geo" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">

	<title>Geographic Resolution</title>

	<section xml:id="tools.geo.introduction">
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>
			The <code>opennlp-geo</code> extension turns place names into places on the map. Where
			the name finder tells an application that a span of text is a location, geographic
			resolution tells it <emphasis>which</emphasis> location: it takes the mention, looks it
			up in a gazetteer of known places, chooses among the candidates that share the name, and
			returns the chosen record with its coordinates. A mention of "Springfield" resolves to
			one of the many Springfields; a document that also mentions "Illinois" pushes the choice
			toward the one in Illinois.
		</para>
		<para>
			The extension is built around two small interfaces. A <code>Gazetteer</code> is a
			lookup over a body of place records. A <code>Geocoder</code> chooses among the
			candidates a gazetteer returns for the mentions in a piece of text. A document annotator
			ties the two into a pipeline, reading the entity layer produced by the name finder and
			adding a layer of resolved locations. Later sections of this chapter add an
			administrative hierarchy over the resolved places and a similarity measure between
			places.
		</para>
		<para>
			The extension bundles a small worldwide gazetteer so it works out of the box, and it
			reads the large open gazetteer formats that an application supplies itself. Consistent
			with the rest of the library, the large data sets are never packaged: the application
			downloads the source it wants and points the loader at it, accepting that source's
			license in doing so.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="tools.geo.gazetteer">
		<title>Gazetteers</title>
		<para>
			A <code>Gazetteer</code> answers three questions about places: which records carry a
			given name, which record a source identifies by its own record id, and which record
			represents a country. Every method may touch backing storage and so may throw
			<code>IOException</code>.
			<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[public interface Gazetteer {

  List<GazetteerEntry> lookup(CharSequence name) throws IOException;

  Optional<GazetteerEntry> byId(String source, String recordId) throws IOException;

  Optional<GazetteerEntry> byRegion(String isoCountryCode) throws IOException;

  Set<String> sources() throws IOException;
}]]></programlisting>
		</para>
		<para>
			A <code>GazetteerEntry</code> is the record of one place. It carries the source it came
			from and that source's record id, the primary name and any alternate names, the location
			as a <code>GeoPoint</code>, the ISO country code, a coarse feature class, a list of the
			identifiers of the places that contain it, and a map of source-specific attributes. The
			<code>GeoPoint</code> holds a latitude and longitude in WGS84 decimal degrees, both
			range-checked when the point is created.
			<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[GeoPoint point = entry.location();
double lat = point.latitude();
double lon = point.longitude();]]></programlisting>
		</para>
		<para>
			The attribute map is how a record carries identifiers that do not belong to the core
			fields, for example a Wikidata id or a census geoid. The keys follow the
			<code>ATTRIBUTE_KEY_*</code> constants published on <code>GazetteerEntry</code>, so an
			application reads an attribute by the same constant a loader wrote it with. The
			administrative hierarchy later in this chapter joins on the
			<code>ATTRIBUTE_KEY_WHOSONFIRST</code> attribute in exactly this way.
		</para>
		<para>
			Three gazetteer implementations ship with the extension. <code>BundledGazetteer</code>
			is a small worldwide gazetteer packaged with the extension and used through
			<code>getInstance</code>; it needs no external data and is the quickest way to try the
			pipeline. <code>GeoNamesGazetteer</code> reads the GeoNames tab-separated format, and
			<code>OvertureGazetteer</code> reads the Overture division format; both are loaded from a
			file or stream the application supplies.
			<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[// bundled, no external data
Gazetteer bundled = BundledGazetteer.getInstance();

// a downloaded GeoNames table the application supplies
Gazetteer geonames = GeoNamesGazetteer.load(Path.of("allCountries.txt"));

// a downloaded Overture division table
Gazetteer overture = OvertureGazetteer.load(Path.of("divisions.tsv"));]]></programlisting>
			The GeoNames and Overture data sets are downloaded by the application from their
			publishers and are not distributed with OpenNLP.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="tools.geo.geocoding">
		<title>Geocoding</title>
		<para>
			A <code>Geocoder</code> resolves the location mentions in a piece of text against a
			gazetteer. It is given the text and the spans of the mentions, and returns one
			<code>GeoResolution</code> per mention it could resolve.
			<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[public interface Geocoder {

  List<GeoResolution> resolve(CharSequence text, List<Span> locationMentions)
      throws IOException;
}]]></programlisting>
			A <code>GeoResolution</code> pairs the mention span with the chosen
			<code>GazetteerEntry</code> and a confidence in the choice.
			<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[public record GeoResolution(Span mention, GazetteerEntry entry, double confidence) { }]]></programlisting>
		</para>
		<para>
			Two geocoders ship with the extension, and both take a gazetteer to resolve against.
			<code>PopulationPriorGeocoder</code> chooses each mention independently, preferring the
			most prominent candidate for the name. <code>SpatialCoherenceGeocoder</code> resolves
			the mentions of a document together, preferring a set of choices that sit near one
			another, so the other places named in a document inform each individual choice.
			<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[Gazetteer gazetteer = BundledGazetteer.getInstance();
Geocoder geocoder = new SpatialCoherenceGeocoder(gazetteer);

List<GeoResolution> resolved = geocoder.resolve(text, mentions);]]></programlisting>
		</para>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="tools.geo.annotator">
		<title>Geocoding in a document pipeline</title>
		<para>
			<code>GeocodeAnnotator</code> runs a geocoder as part of a document pipeline. It reads
			the entity layer produced by the name finder, resolves the location mentions among those
			entities, and provides a locations layer whose annotations carry the full
			<code>GeoResolution</code> for each resolved mention. It requires
			<code>Layers.ENTITIES</code> and provides its own <code>LOCATIONS</code> key.
			<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[Gazetteer gazetteer = BundledGazetteer.getInstance();
Geocoder geocoder = new SpatialCoherenceGeocoder(gazetteer);

DocumentAnalyzer analyzer = DocumentAnalyzer.builder()
    .add(new SentenceDetectorAnnotator(sentenceDetector))
    .add(new TokenizerAnnotator(tokenizer))
    .add(new NameFinderAnnotator(locationFinder))
    .add(new GeocodeAnnotator(geocoder))
    .build();

Document document = analyzer.analyze(text);

for (Annotation<GeoResolution> location : document.get(GeocodeAnnotator.LOCATIONS)) {
  GeoResolution resolution = location.value();
  GeoPoint point = resolution.entry().location();
  System.out.println(resolution.mention().getCoveredText(text)
      + " -> " + resolution.entry().name()
      + " (" + point.latitude() + ", " + point.longitude() + ")");
}]]></programlisting>
		</para>
		<para>
			By default the annotator geocodes the entities whose type is
			<literal>location</literal>, matched without regard to case. A second constructor takes
			the set of entity type labels to treat as locations, so a pipeline whose name finder
			labels places differently, or under more than one label, names those labels instead.
			<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[new GeocodeAnnotator(geocoder, Set.of("location", "gpe"));]]></programlisting>
			The locations layer keeps the original mention spans, so a resolved place lines up with
			the entity it came from and with every other layer in the document.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="tools.geo.hierarchy">
		<title>Administrative hierarchy</title>
		<para>
			A resolved place sits inside larger places: a neighborhood inside a city, the city
			inside a state, the state inside a country. A <code>PlaceHierarchy</code> answers, for a
			given place identifier, the chain of places that contain it, nearest first.
			<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[public interface PlaceHierarchy {

  List<PlaceAncestor> ancestors(String id);
}]]></programlisting>
			Each <code>PlaceAncestor</code> carries the identifier, name, and type of one enclosing
			place, and a <code>ContainmentChain</code> is the ordered list of them from the nearest
			enclosing place out to the largest. The place whose ancestors are requested is not itself
			part of the chain.
		</para>
		<para>
			<code>ContainmentSpine</code> is a hierarchy built from a table the application supplies.
			Its builder takes places one at a time, or reads them in bulk from one of two formats. A
			neutral tab-separated table lists <code>id</code>, <code>parent_id</code>,
			<code>name</code>, and <code>type</code> per line, with an empty parent for a root; a
			result exported from a knowledge base that records administrative containment drops
			straight into this format. A Who's On First meta CSV is read by its own header columns
			<code>id</code>, <code>parent_id</code>, <code>name</code>, and <code>placetype</code>.
			<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[// a neutral containment table the application assembles
PlaceHierarchy fromTable = ContainmentSpine.builder()
    .addTable(Path.of("containment.tsv"))
    .build();

// a Who's On First meta CSV the application downloads
PlaceHierarchy fromWof = ContainmentSpine.builder()
    .addWofMeta(Path.of("whosonfirst-admin-meta.csv"))
    .build();

// or place by place
PlaceHierarchy hierarchy = ContainmentSpine.builder()
    .add("parkslope", "brooklyn", "Park Slope", "neighbourhood")
    .add("brooklyn", "nyc", "Brooklyn", "borough")
    .add("nyc", "nystate", "New York City", "locality")
    .add("nystate", "usa", "New York", "region")
    .add("usa", null, "United States", "country")
    .build();]]></programlisting>
			The identifiers here are the application's own; a real spine uses the identifiers of the
			source it was built from. Asking for the ancestors of a place returns the enclosing
			places, nearest first, and not the place itself:
			<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[for (PlaceAncestor ancestor : hierarchy.ancestors("parkslope")) {
  System.out.println(ancestor.name());
}]]></programlisting>
			prints
			<screen><![CDATA[Brooklyn
New York City
New York
United States]]></screen>
			As with the large gazetteers, the Who's On First data is downloaded by the application
			and is not distributed with OpenNLP.
		</para>
		<para>
			<code>HierarchyAnnotator</code> adds the containment chain of each resolved place to a
			document. It requires the locations layer produced by the geocoder and provides its own
			<code>CONTAINMENT</code> key, one <code>ContainmentChain</code> per resolved place whose
			identifier the hierarchy knows. It reads the identifier from a gazetteer attribute on the
			resolved entry, by default <code>ATTRIBUTE_KEY_WHOSONFIRST</code>; a second constructor
			takes the attribute key to use, so a spine keyed on another identifier joins on that
			attribute instead.
			<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[DocumentAnalyzer analyzer = DocumentAnalyzer.builder()
    .add(new SentenceDetectorAnnotator(sentenceDetector))
    .add(new TokenizerAnnotator(tokenizer))
    .add(new NameFinderAnnotator(locationFinder))
    .add(new GeocodeAnnotator(geocoder))
    .add(new HierarchyAnnotator(hierarchy))
    .build();

Document document = analyzer.analyze(text);

for (Annotation<ContainmentChain> annotation : document.get(HierarchyAnnotator.CONTAINMENT)) {
  StringBuilder path = new StringBuilder();
  for (PlaceAncestor ancestor : annotation.value().ancestors()) {
    if (path.length() > 0) {
      path.append(" -> ");
    }
    path.append(ancestor.name());
  }
  System.out.println(path);
}]]></programlisting>
			For a mention resolved to the Park Slope place above, the annotation on the containment
			layer holds that place's enclosing chain, the same
			<literal>Brooklyn, New York City, New York, United States</literal> that
			<code>ancestors</code> returns; the resolved place itself is not part of the chain. A
			place the hierarchy does not know contributes no annotation, and nothing is invented for
			a missing join.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="tools.geo.profiles">
		<title>Place similarity</title>
		<para>
			Two places can be alike without sharing a name or appearing together in text. Place
			similarity compares places by what is measured about them: population density, median
			income, transit access, whatever an application chooses to record. Each place carries a
			numeric profile, and two places are similar when their profiles are.
		</para>
		<para>
			<code>PlaceProfiles</code> loads a table the application supplies. The table is
			tab-separated, with a header of <code>id</code> followed by one column per metric, then
			one place per line with its identifier and one value per metric.
			<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[id	density	income	transit
park-slope	38000	95000	9
brooklyn-heights	36000	110000	9
suburbia	2000	85000	2
rural-town	150	45000	1]]></programlisting>
			At load the columns are standardized to mean zero and unit variance, so metrics measured
			in different units contribute comparably rather than the largest-numbered column
			dominating. A column that never varies contributes nothing.
			<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[PlaceProfiles profiles = PlaceProfiles.load(Path.of("place-profiles.tsv"));]]></programlisting>
		</para>
		<para>
			Places compare by the cosine of their standardized profiles, in the range minus one to
			one, and <code>mostSimilar</code> ranks the other places by that measure.
			<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[double alike = profiles.similarity("park-slope", "brooklyn-heights");

for (PlaceProfiles.Neighbor neighbor : profiles.mostSimilar("park-slope", 5)) {
  System.out.println(neighbor.id() + "\t" + neighbor.similarity());
}]]></programlisting>
			The measure is grounded entirely in the supplied metrics, so the quality of the result
			follows the quality of the table. Assembling metric tables from public sources such as
			census and tax data is a data task an application takes on itself; the engine and its
			table format are what the extension provides.
		</para>
	</section>

</chapter>
