<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML 5.0//EN"
"http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/dtd/docbook.dtd"[
]>
<!-- Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more contributor
	license agreements. See the NOTICE file distributed with this work for additional
	information regarding copyright ownership. The ASF licenses this file to
	you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License"); you may not use
	this file except in compliance with the License. You may obtain a copy of
	the License at http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0 Unless required
	by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed under the
	License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS
	OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the License for the specific
	language governing permissions and limitations under the License. -->

<chapter xml:id="tools.noise" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">

	<title>Noise Scoring</title>

	<section xml:id="tools.noise.introduction">
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>
			Between clean text and outright garbage sits a spectrum: words mangled by
			optical recognition, stretches of keyboard mash, runs shaped like encoded
			binary. The package <code>opennlp.tools.noise</code> scores such stretches on
			the <code>opennlp:noise</code> layer in four severity tiers, mildest to worst:
			<code>misspelled</code>, <code>damaged</code>, <code>gibberish</code>, and
			<code>binaryish</code>. Each finding carries a score within its tier, so
			consumers set their own thresholds, and a masking or filtering step downstream
			decides what to do about each tier.
		</para>
		<para>
			The built-in scorer uses structural signals only and ships no data. The
			signals are calibrated so the most consonant-heavy legitimate English words
			stay below every threshold, and they apply to ASCII-letter tokens only, so
			text in other scripts is never flagged. Two tiers take evidence the caller
			supplies: <code>misspelled</code> only fires with a dictionary, and in the
			annotator's default mode spans the embedded-asset detector already explained
			are excluded, so a payload is never reported twice.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="tools.noise.scoring">
		<title>Scoring text</title>
		<para>
			The scorer takes the text and the spans to leave out. With a dictionary, a
			token one known confusion repair away from a word is reported as misspelled,
			the shape optical recognition damage takes; adjacent findings merge into one
			span:
			<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
Set<String> words = Set.of("modern", "times");
NoiseScorer scorer = new StructuralNoiseScorer(words::contains);

String text = "rnodern tirnes and zxkcvbnmsdfg";
for (NoiseSpan noise : scorer.score(text, List.of())) {
    System.out.println(noise.severity() + " " + noise.span());
}]]>
			</programlisting>
			This prints one line per finding; <code>rnodern tirnes</code> repairs to the
			two dictionary words through the <code>rn</code> to <code>m</code> confusion
			and merges into one span, and the mash carries two agreeing structural
			signals:
			<programlisting><![CDATA[
misspelled [0..14)
gibberish [19..31)]]>
			</programlisting>
			Without a dictionary the same call reports only the gibberish: the misspelled
			tier demands evidence, not guesses.
			<code>NoiseManualExampleTest</code> asserts the behavior shown here.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="tools.noise.pipeline">
		<title>The noise layer and the asset hand-off</title>
		<para>
			<code>NoiseAnnotator</code> provides <code>opennlp:noise</code>. In its
			default mode it requires <code>opennlp:assets</code> and excludes those spans
			from scoring, so an embedded binary is explained once, by the asset layer, and
			never again as noise. The standalone mode scores the whole text and requires
			nothing:
			<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
Document document = new AssetAnnotator().annotate(Document.of(text));
document = new NoiseAnnotator().annotate(document);

List<Annotation<NoiseSpan>> noise = document.get(NoiseAnnotator.NOISE);]]>
			</programlisting>
			Because findings are spans on a layer, masking composes directly: replacing
			the covered characters of every noise annotation with a fixed character
			renders an unreadable stretch as, for example, a run of stars, with every
			offset unchanged.
		</para>
	</section>
</chapter>
